Nearly every application you write will require menus. NetBeans provides a very easy-to-use interface to
build and implement Swing menus. Swing menus are capable of much more than the typical menu.
Swing allows multiple menus on components and frames, and the location of menus can be set by the layout manager.
For our example though, we'll go
with a typical menu at the top of the frame. Swing allows icon images in menu items, and you can easily add
keyboard shortcuts to items as well. You can also make use of checkboxes and radio buttons in a menu.
You will also see that it's easy to build submenus within a menu.
Then we'll learn about pop-up menus as well. And, of course, we will write code in our even handlers to make
our menus do something useful.
Let's jump right in and try it out. Let's use our existing desktop GUI for the example.
To start, let's drag a JMenuBar to the top of the frame. The JMenuBar is preloaded with File and Edit
placeholder menus, but there are no menu items under them. You can add a menu item by right-clicking the
File menu and selecting Add From Palette Menu Item. Then we can right-click the new item and edit text.
Let's call it New. If I double-click the shortcut box here, the window opens to select a keyboard shortcut.
I could select these manually, but I'm lazy, so I'll click in the Key Stroke area here and enter the keys
directly from the keyboard. Let's use Ctrl+N. Now I can also add an image icon here using the icon property
similar to what we have done before. (Working) I have an image for our example.
Okay, let's add a separator, Add From Palette, Separator. Let's add another menu item and call it Open. (Working)
Add another image icon (Working) and set its keyboard shortcut to Ctrl+O.
Now another separator and one last menu item, and call it Exit with a shortcut of Ctrl+Q.
Now I want to change the name of the next menu, so right-click, Edit Text, and call it View.
Let's add three menu items, and we'll use these to set our internal frame's visibility.
So we'll add Window 1 with a shortcut of Ctrl+1, Window 2 with a shortcut of Ctrl+2, and Window 3 with a
shortcut of Ctrl+3. Now if we want to add an additional menu, right-click the menu bar and select Add Menu.
Let's call this one, Help. Now I want to add a submenu, so I select Add From Palette, Menu.
Let's call it Contents. Then add a Menu Item and call it Index.
And lastly, another Menu Item called Getting Started. Okay, let's run the application and see what it looks like. (Running)
All of our items appear, and our submenus appear as well. Next, we'll add checkboxes and radio buttons to menus.