Swing menus allow checkboxes and radio buttons as menu items. In fact, all menu items extend a class called
abstract button as menus do behave much the same way as buttons do, if you think about it.
Let's add a new menu. Now I'll attempt its location over to the left of Help.
Oops, I missed. Let me try again. Okay, let's call this menu CheckBox, then Add From Palette, Menu Item/CheckBox.
Let's add several. I'm not going to bother naming these. Let's add another menu and call it Radio.
I want to move this one over too. I'm getting better at this. Let's Add From Palette, Menu Item/RadioButton.
Again, let's add several. (Working) Now, radio buttons usually only allow one selection, so we'll need to add
a radio button group. As expected, the group is invisible, but shows up in the inspector.
Let's select all three RadioButton items and select our buttonGroup.
It's time to run it and try it out. Our CheckBox items can be selected or deselected, and our RadioButton
items behave as a group allowing only one to be selected at a time.
Now, let's move forward and add real event code to our examples.