Let's create some events that make our menus actually do something worthwhile.
Let's start with a simple example, the exit menu item. To create the event code, all we need to do is select
the menu item and double-click. NetBeans created our method here.
To close the application, we'll use a common method, System.exit 0.
Let's see if it works. (Running) That's perfect. Now let's try again and use the keyboard shortcut Ctrl+Q.
That works as well. Now when we built our desktop application, we added the closable property to
jInternalFrame1, but had no option to reopen that window. Let's fix that now.
So let's double-click the Window 1 menu item. I want to search for the code that was initially generated to
make jInternalFrame1 visible. (Searching) First we'll need jInternalFrame.setVisible(true), and I'll copy
and paste that into our method. And since this application uses a desktop pane, I'll also need to add the
internal frame to the desktop again. I can do that with this code here, which adds the internal frame to the
desktop pane's DEFAULT_LAYER. That's all we need, so let's run it. (Running)
First, let's close Window1, then try out our menu. That works.
Let's also try out the shortcut, Ctrl+1. That works too. Now let's do something extra special.
I'm going to show you how to create another GUI and link DesktopGUI to it.
So let's create a New JFrame Form and call it AboutGUI and the same package, com.Pluralsight.
This is going to be an about window for our application, so let's make it smaller and add a text area. (Working)
Let's select lineWrap and wrapStyleWord, then create some fake text.
Of course you could add anything here that you wish. Then let's go back to our DesktopGUI, create a new menu
item under the Help menu called About. Let's double-click it and generate the event method.
By the way, you may have noticed that the event methods created here are the ActionPerformed methods just like buttons.
Now to create a link to AboutGUI, I type new AboutGUI.setVisible(true), and that's it.
Let's run it. (Running) Now the About menu calls AboutGUI. Oops, when I close AboutGUI, DesktopGUI also closes.
No worries. To fix that, let's go to AboutGUI, select its JFrame, and change the property,
defaultCloseOperation, which is by default set to exit on close.
Let's change it to DISPOSE, which will only dispose of the AboutGUI window and not close our entire application.
Let's go back to DesktopGUI and run it. (Running) Now the about window closes leaving our application still running.
Just a bonus piece of useful knowledge for you. Next, we'll have a look at pop-up menus.