Another type of menu we need to learn about is the pop-up menu.
Now when I drag a pop-up menu into the design area, it of course is invisible, but does appear in the
inspector window under Other Components. We'll have to build the menu here, so right-click,
Add From Palette, Menu Item. Let's add several. (Working) Let's change the text of each to let's say Yes,
No, and Maybe. We'll need to add some event handling code as well.
Here we might expect the user to click on the desktop pane, so we'll place it there.
We'll want to select Events, Mouse, mousePressed. And to make this function across all platforms,
we'll also have to duplicate the code in Events, Mouse, mouseReleased since some platforms treat this differently.
We have to check that this mouse event occurred while over our desktop pane, so this is done with the method isPopupTrigger.
To show the pop-up, we type jPopupMenu1.show (Typing) with evt.getComponent.
And to make the pop-up appear where the user clicked, we use evt.getX and evt.getY.
Now we'll need to copy this into the mouseReleased method as well.
Let's see if it works. (Running) Now, if I right-click on the desktop, our menu appears wherever I clicked.
You can of course then add event handling code to each of its menu items.