In this module, we're going to download and install NetBeans, then we'll explore some of its features and
structure, and after we're going to build an actual application, so you'll have a really good idea of what
NetBeans and Swing can do by the end of this module.
First, we're going to go open a browser. We'll go to netbeans.org.
And as you see on the home page, we'll click the Learn More button, and under Documentation click on the link
for Release Notes and then on System Requirements. You might want to look this over to see if their
requirements match your machine. Also, a little further down here we see Required Software.
Okay, in the last module we installed the JRE, the Java Runtime Environment, but NetBeans actually requires
the Java Development Kit that contains the additional developer tools for compiling and debugging.
We're going to need this. If you already have it installed, make sure that you have JDK 7u21.
That's the release that's necessary to run applications in NetBeans.
So let's go back to the home page here, and we'll click on the Download button.
We'll have several choices here. If you scroll down in the text below, it explains that you can download the
JDK separately, standalone, or in a bundle with NetBeans. If you already have the JDK installed on your machine,
you have two choices above. You can get the Java SE version or the Java EE version.
If you're a serious Java programmer and you might require in future the server like GlassFish or Apache Tomcat,
download the Java EE version. Otherwise, you can just download the Java SE version.
What we're going to do though is download the latest JDK with NetBeans IDE in a bundle, so click that link.
You'll have to accept the license agreement. If you want to read that, go right ahead.
Choose the proper version for your machine. If you have Windows, the x86 is actually the 32-bit version.
Windows x64 is the 64-bit version. I'm going to click on the x86 version myself, and it begins the download.
You can pause here. I'm going to go get a cup of coffee while you finish the download.
Let me know when you're done.
Okay great, we've completed the download. Now let's go over to the Downloads page on your browser.
You'll see the exe file in my case. We'll click on that. It will come up and ask us if we want to continue
with the program installation, Yes, and it will bring up the installer.
This is going to take you a few minutes, so I'm going to get another pot of coffee, and we'll move on.
In the next module, we'll open up NetBeans and explore what it can do.