Great, you've got NetBeans installed. Now let's spend some time exploring its features.
First, you'll notice that the Start Page comes up automatically.
You'll see links here to sample projects and tutorials included with NetBeans, but I recommend that you
finish this course first, then move on to more advanced topics if you're interested in doing so.
You can uncheck the Show On Startup checkbox here if you don't want to see the startup page every time you open NetBeans.
If you want to see it again later, you can always pull it up by going to Help and pulling down to Start Page.
For now, let's just close it out. Okay, to see the structure of NetBeans and what it can do, we need to actually
create a project, so we're going to start right off here, create New Project from the File menu.
You'll see a list of categories for different sorts of applications.
Choose Java and Java Application. So our project is going to be a trivial little application called the
Kilometer Converter. It will give us a great example of everything NetBeans can do, but it will be rather
easy to build. So we need to name the project. Let's call it KilometerConverterProject as the project name.
You can leave the project location and project folder fields set to their default values or click the Browse
button to choose an alternate location on your system. Make sure to deselect the Create Main Class checkbox.
We won't need that for now. Leaving this option selected generates a new class as the main entry point for the
application, but our main GUI window created in the next step will serve that purpose, so checking this box
is not necessary. Click the Finish button when you are done. Now you'll see the project appears in the Projects
pane in the upper left-hand corner of the IDE. Now right-click on the KilometerConverterProject name and
choose New, JFrame Form. JFrame is the Swing class component responsible for the main frame of your application.
Next, type KilometerConverterGUI as the class name and com.Pluralsight as the package name.
You can actually name this package anything you want, but here we're following the standard coding conventions.
The remainder of the field should automatically be filled in. Click the Finish button when you are done.
When the IDE finishes loading, let's familiarize you briefly about just some of the features of the NetBeans IDE.
In the upper right-hand corner, you will see the Palette pane. It is here that you will find all the components
available in the Swing API. Most of these may look familiar to you.
This is where we will choose our application's components. The Design area in the top center pane is where
you will visually construct your GUI. It has two views, Source View, and Design View, Design View being the default.
You can toggle between views at any time by clicking their respective tabs.
Source View will show you the actual source code for the class.
Let's go ahead and click on the Source View tab. Notice the pluses and minuses along the left that allow you
to expand and to hide sections of code. Expand all of the sections if they are not already.
You will see NetBeans has automatically generated code that is commonly expected, such as the user clicking
the close button on the window. This code appears in uneditable blue sections of code called guarded blocks.
Now programmers that like to have complete control over their application might not like the idea of not being
able to edit these, but this is pretty much standard code that you can rely upon and won't need to change.
Have a look at the private method, initComponents, which initializes the various components of the GUI.
It also tells the application to exit on close, preform some layout specific tasks, then packs the soon-to-be
added components together on the screen. Don't feel that you need to understand this code in any detail just yet.
Okay, the next pane we'll explore is the property editor located just below the palette.
This area allows you to edit all the properties of each component.
The property editor is easy to use, allowing you to click and edit individual properties for a component without
entering the source code directly. The next pane is the inspector located at the bottom left.
The inspector shows us a graphical representation of our application's components.
Currently we only have the JFrame component, but after we add a few more you'll be able to click on each
component, and its properties will appear in the property editor.
Okay, you can save this for now, and in the next section we're going to build our GUI application.