Okay, let's design our first application. First, let's set the title of our application that will appear in
the title bar. Click once on the JFrame object in the inspector window.
Then edit the title in the property editor to read Kilometer Converter.
You won't see the title appear just yet in the Design area, but it will show up when we run the actual application.
Next, let's drag a jTextField from the Palette to the upper left-hand corner of the Design area.
As you approach the upper left corner, the GUI builder provides visual cues that suggest appropriate spacing.
We'll add more explicit names for each component and alter the text within the fields later.
For now, we'll continue just adding all the necessary components.
Next, let's drag a jLabel onto the Design area, place it to the right of the jTextField, again watching for
visual cues that suggest an appropriate amount of spacing. We'll make sure the text base is aligned with
that of the jTextField. Okay, now let's drag a jButton from the Palette and position it to the left and
underneath the jTextField. Again, the visual cues help guide it into place.
Finally, let's add a second jLabel, placing it to the right of the jButton.
Great! All of our GUI components are now in place. Let's make some adjustments and give everything the
proper names as well. First, click the jTextField and blank out the default text.
When you erase the text from the jTextField, it will shrink in size.
Don't worry about that for now; we'll fix that in just a minute.
Now click on the jButton, then change the text of the jButton from jButton1 to Convert.
Also, change the top jLabel text to Miles and the bottom jLabel to Kilometers.
Now we can fix that pesky little jTextField. Click it, and Shift+Click the jButton as well, right-click,
Ctrl+Click for Mac users, and pull down to Same Size, Same Width.
The components now snap to the same width. When you perform this step, make sure the JFrame itself is not also selected.
If it is, the Same Size menu will not be active. Finally, grab the lower right-hand corner of the JFrame and
adjust its size to eliminate any extra white space. Note that if you eliminate all of the extra space,
the title, which only appears at runtime, may not show completely.
The end user is free to resize the application as desired, but you may want to leave some extra space on the
right side to make sure that everything fits correctly. The GUI portion of this application is now complete.
NetBeans has done most of the work for us, and creating this GUI was simple, if not a trivial task.
Now, take a minute to click on the Source tab. You might be surprised that the amount of code that has been generated.
Remember that you might have to click the plus or minus signs along the left to expand out your code sections.
Now, all that's left for us to do is add the application's logic, which by the way is what programmers should
be focusing on, not wasting time building layouts. Let's begin by giving our components names that make sense.
Right-click the jTextField component in the inspector pane and choose Change Variable Name.
Let's call it milesTextField. Next, jLabel1, let's change that to milesLabel.
Next, jButton1, and we'll call it convertButton. And lastly, jLabel2, and we'll call it kilometerLabel.
Our source code will automatically be updated with the new names.
When a user interacts with a Swing GUI component, such as clicking the Convert button, that component will
generate a special kind of object called an event object, which it will then broadcast to any other objects
that have previously registered themselves as listeners for that event.
The NetBeans IDE makes event listener registration extremely simple.
In the Design area, let's click on the Convert button to select it.
Make sure that only the Convert button is selected. If the JFrame is also selected, this step will not work.
Right-click the Convert button and choose Events, Action, actionPerformed.
This will generate the required event handling code leaving you with empty method bodies in which to add your own functionality.
There are many different event types representing the various kinds of actions that a user can take like
clicking the mouse, typing on the keyboard, moving the mouse. Our application is only concerned with the
action event for now. The next step will be to add the actual code to convert miles to kilometers.
As you can see, NetBeans has generated a method called convertButtonActionPerformed.
Code placed within this method will execute when the Convert button is clicked.
We simply need to obtain the number that the user entered in the milesTextField, perform a calculation that
converts it to kilometers, then set the kilometer label to display the answer.
So let's comment everything as we go to keep things clear. To get the user's input from the milesTextField,
we'll write this code. We want the answer to be a double so that we can have a decimal number,
and we'll call it inputNumber. Then we'll convert the text in the milesTextField to a double.
Then we calculate and set the answer. (Typing) So let's create another double and call it answer. (Typing)
To convert miles to kilometers, we multiply miles by 1.609344, and the F designates the number as a decimal
of a float type. Lastly, to set the kilometer label with the answer, we say this.kilometerLabel.setText in
parenthesis, answer, which is our variable, + the string, space, kilometers.
This concatenates and converts the numeric answer along with the string kilometers with a space to a string
we can display in the kilometer label. Okay, let's run this and see what happens.
Simply click Run and Run Main Project here at the top. The first time you run an application, you will be
prompted with a dialog asking to set KilometerConverterGUI as the main class for the project.
Click the OK button, and when the program finishes compiling you will see the application running in its own window.
Let's enter a number. In the Miles text field click the Convert button, and the answer appears.
Now there are two problems with this code. As you'll see, some numbers convert to kilometers with way too
many decimal places. We can fix that. Also, the user could possibly enter non-numeric text in the Miles
text field, and that would break our code. But we can fix that too, so let's close the application and go
back to our code. For the first fix, we'll use a class in Java called DecimalFormat that will limit the
answer to two decimal places. We'll create a new DecimalFormat object, let's call it df, and we will limit
it to two decimal places represented by this string of pound signs, this pattern.
Then we'll format the answer using df.format method. The format method will return a string instead of a
double, so we'll need to change that type. We have an exclamation point over here denoting an error.
The class can't find the DecimalFormat class. So clicking on the light bulb, we can have NetBeans
automatically add the import for that class. (Typing) Now, for the next fix we'll need to enclose this line
of code here in a try-catch block. Any non-numeric numbers entered will throw an exception.
We can catch that exception and display a message to the user using the JOptionPane class.
It has a method called showMessageDialog. The parameters for this method are this, which represents the
parent component, a message telling the user to please enter a valid number; (Typing) the title,
which we'll call Error for this message window; and we'll use a standard JOptionPane type for errors. (Working)
One more problem now we've declared the variable input number inside of a try-catch block, so it's out of
scope for the code following, so we need to extract that out and put it at the top of the method like so.
That's it. Let's run the application once again and check it out.
Now any number I enter is limited to two decimal places, (Typing) and if I enter text into the Miles field
an error message appears. There you go. You've built your first Swing application that will run on any
platform that runs Java. Now you may have a better understanding of the ease and power of using Swing and
NetBeans as a tool to build quite complex GUI interfaces in a short period of time and how this can
expand your worth as a programmer.
Next, we'll take a closer look at Swing's components, containers, and menus.