In this module, you've learned about the NetBeans IDE and the Java Development Kit that it requires.
You've learned about the Palette, Properties, Design, and Inspector panes of NetBeans.
You've seen the advantage of NetBeans creating automatically generated code, such as the initComponents
method that sets up the window layout and window closing code automatically.
You have been introduced to Swing's labels, text fields, and buttons.
You've learned about event listeners and how to use the actionPerformed method for a button.
You've learned about how to retrieve text from a text field and parse it to a number, and you've learned to set
text in a label. We've even introduced a very useful Java class called DecimalFormat.
And you've been introduced to just one of Swing's dialog windows using the JOptionPane.showMessageDialog method.
Now let's learn more about each of Swing's components.