In this module, we're going to take a closer look at Swing components from labels to text fields and text
areas, buttons, lists, and combo boxes, spinners, sliders, progress bars, tables, and trees.
Let's just get right to it.
Open up NetBeans. First we'll need to start a new project, Java, Java Application.
Click Next. We'll call it SwingComponentProject. If the Create Main Class checkbox is checked,
make sure that it's unchecked because we don't need to do that. Click Finish.
Okay, so now we'll need to create our JForm, so right-click on the project, click New and JFrame From.
We'll call it SwingComponentGUI. We'll give the package name com.Pluralsight and click Finish.
Okay, we have our JFrame form. Let's add several labels and text boxes for the example I want to show you.
So first we'll add a label here, Label1, Label2, and Label3. Three text boxes, text fields, excuse me. (Working)
Okay, let's give these names so that they make sense later. For our first field, we'll call it First Name,
the next one Middle Name, and next Last Name. (Typing) Let's line up these fields just a little bit,
make it look better. Now let's change the variable names for these so they make more sense programmatically later on.
Let's call the first one firstNameLabel, change the variable name to middleNameLabel, and, you guessed it,
lastNameLabel. Our text fields, firstNameField, middleNameField, and lastNameField.
Let's select all of the text fields, and we'll set the number of columns within the box to 12.
This will hold them at that size. So, as you saw before, when we get rid of the text in the field,
they will not shrink. They will maintain the 12-column size. That's their preferred size.
So we'll lose all the text in the fields. Now, an interesting trick with labels is you can use something called
a pneumonic, so we'll give the first one a pneumonical F, the next one M, and the last one L.
This will allow us to use keyboard commands to give focus to the text fields.
So for first name we need to put the label for firstNameField, the label for middleNameField for the next one,
and the label for lastNameField for the last one. This will make it focus on the text field when we hit Alt+F,
Alt+M, or Alt+L. Let's run it, and we'll show you. As usual, you have to OK that this is the main class.
Notice that the first characters of each label are underlined indicating that they have a keyboard command
associated with them. If I type in Alt+L, that text field gains focus.
Alt+M and Alt+F, it works just fine. It's a nice little trick. Okay, let's have a look at some of the properties
of text fields. You can add an icon, an image if you wish. Let's import it to the project so it's part of it. (Working)
So you can have images and text co-existing within a label. You can also line up the text on either side of
the label using the horizontalTextPosition property. You can have different spacing by setting the iconTextGap.
For now, let's just reset that back to default. Now also you can have borders with a label if you wish,
that's Bevel Border here, different ones you can experiment with.
Let's try the Line Border, see what that looks like. You can play around all you want, but let's set this
back to default. Now with a text field, you can set the background to any color you wish if you feel that's
something you want to do. A text field can be editable. Usually that's set programmatically, but there is a
checkbox here to gray out the fields so the user can't input anything.
Foreground color would actually give the text a specific color.
You can set the alignment of the text within the field. You can set tooltips for a field, so let's say Help Me.
And let's run it, and we'll show you what the tooltip looks like.
There you go. Also, you can set any sort of font and size in bold or whatever.
And you can set borders, of course, on text fields as well. (Working)
Let's add another label here, and we'll call this one Password.
Let's change the variable name to passwordLabel. There's a special kind of text field called a Password
Field, and of course it comes up with the asterisks to hide what was typed.
Let's set its columns for 12 as well, let's clear out the text in the field, and let's run it.
As you can see, anything typed in this field shows up with the standard asterisks to hide the text.
Now let's have a look at a text area. Text areas allow the user to type in a large amount of text.
You'll see down here on the left it's automatically enclosed in a JScroll pane.
So if text is typed beyond the limits of the box area, scroll bars will appear.
Let's call it the bioTextArea. So our user can enter a bio. Let's put a label in here as well, call it bio,
bioLabel, and the name Bio. So let's run this and see what a text area looks like.
Let's type some text in. As you can see, there's no line wrapping.
Scroll bars appear automatically, but we would probably like to use the line wrap feature, which is one of
the properties of a text area, so we check that. Let's run it again. (Typing)
Now as we type, you'll see that it does line wrap. But look, it wraps right in the middle of a word.
We can fix that as well. So there's another property called wrapStyleWord, which will prevent that from happening.
Let's run it one last time. (Typing) That looks a lot better. (Typing)
Now if I keep on typing and fill up this whole area with text, you'll see the scroll bars automatically
appear, and it will not increase the size of the text area I have allowed here. (Working)
You could also set the fonts for a text area, of course the same old stuff.
You can set the color of the background if you wish. You can set the color of the foreground for the fonts.
You can set borders. Most components have these options. Now there's one final type of text field I want to
show you, so let's add another label and call it phoneLabel. (Typing)
Let's change its text to Phone. Then we'll add a FormattedTextField.
Let's make it 12 columns just like the others, clear out its text.
The interesting thing about a formatted field is this property formatterFactory.
This allows you to constrain text to specific formats, such as numbers, dates, times, percentage, currency,
or any specific pattern you want. Since this is a phone number, we'll use the custom mask.
It's already close to what we want, but we'll have to add an area code as well.
Now let's run it. Text entered here will automatically conform to the phone number format we wish.
So we've covered the basics of labels and text fields. Next, we'll learn about the various types of buttons,
including toggle buttons, radio buttons, and check boxes. Now let's move on and explore buttons.