It's probably obvious now that buttons contain the same properties we've already discussed such as background,
foreground, font, icons, pneumonics, borders, and so on. Let's put a button here and change the name of it.
We'll call this on Submit. Previously, we discussed how to add the ActionPerformed method to a button,
so we're not going to do that again. For now, let's move on and add toggle buttons.
Unlike regular buttons, toggle buttons maintain two different states basically, selected and deselected.
Let's call this one Agree. (Working) As we run the application, we can see the toggle button's behavior
selected and deselected. (Working) Let's add a second toggle button and call it Disagree. (Working)
We can tie these two toggle buttons together using something called a Button Group.
As we drag the button group into the design area, it is invisible, but, as you can see, it appears in the
inspector window over here. Let's change its variable name to toggleButtonGroup. (Typing)
Now, if we select the Agree button, you can see that our toggleButtonGroup appears in its property for
buttonGroup, and we can assign this button to that group. Let's also do the same for the Disagree button. (Working)
Now when we run the application, selecting one deselects the other.
In this case, it probably makes more sense to have the Agree button initially selected.
We can set that in the Agree button's properties. Now if we run it again, you can see Agree is selected from the start.
Now let's check out radio buttons. Let's add three of them (Working) and call them Single, Married,
and Divorced/Widowed. Radio buttons are almost always in a button group.
Let's create another group and call it radioButtonGroup. Now we can select all three radio buttons and assign
them to our group. Let's run it and check it out. You could choose to have one initially selected or not.
Okay, lastly let's explore check boxes. These are not usually placed in button groups as the user is allowed
most of the time to check more than one. Let's call this one I agree to the terms, and this one Please send
me a newsletter. (Typing) Let's give the application a little extra space and run it.
As you can see, the check boxes act as expected. Next, we'll explore lists and combo boxes.