Now let's learn about lists and combo boxes. First, we'll need to make a bit more room to add the new components.
Let's drag a list onto the application and resize it a bit. There's an odd bug with NetBeans.
I'm looking to alter a property called model, but it only shows up after I deselect the list, then reselect it.
There it is. Now it shows up. Of course you can apply all of the common properties to list we've mentioned previously.
Let's click on the model, and as you'll see, these are the list's items.
Let's change the items to say favorite colors. (Working) Run the application, and you see it's not only possible
to select one item in the list, but also by control clicking you can select multiple items.
Let's add an event listener to this list. We right-click Events, ListSelection, valueChanged.
This creates the method jList1ValueChanged. For now, let's just print out a string to the console when an
event is triggered. (Typing) We'll run it. You can see that two events are triggered.
This is happening because although a new event is triggered by the user selecting an item, also an event is
triggered because another item is deselected. This is the way list events are designed.
We can get around this problem by using a method in the ListSelectionEvent called getValueIsAdjusting.
This will trigger only once. (Working) Now just to double-check, we'll print to the console once more,
(Working) run it again, and yes it's only triggering once. Now let's see a more practical example.
We'll lose the console print statement, go back to the Design view, and add a label to print selection results.
Back to Source view, and I'll say jLabel1.setText jList1.getSelectedValue, (Working) and we'll have to change
this to a string value using the toString method. Run it again.
And as we select values in the list, they are written to the label, but what if I select multiple values?
This doesn't work. I can change the method to getSelectedValuesList, which returns an array of strings instead.
Run it, and now it returns single values and also multiple values.
Okay, let's lose the label and its related code. NetBeans doesn't allow me to delete the entire method because
that was generated code. But that's okay. I can just delete the body of the method instead.
Now let's add some combo boxes. Let's add three to represent a date, day, month, and year.
Once again, for the model property to appear, I must deselect and select.
Clicking on model allows me to edit the items in the combo box.
I'll put 1 through 12 for the months, (Typing) just a few for the days, I'm not going to type 30, (Typing)
and just a few options for year. (Typing) Run the application, and you can see how combo boxes appear. (Working)
Now if we want to listen to events from a combo box, we use our old friend, actionPerformed.
We get the item selected with this code, this.jComboBox3.getSelectedItem.
We'll want this as a string, so let's create a String variable and call it selection.
Then we'll need to add the toString method. Let's print this out to the console just to verify. (Typing)
Let's run it, (waiting) and the selected items are printed. Next up, we'll look at spinners, sliders,
and progress bars. Now it's time to explore spinners, sliders, and progress bars.