Let's begin with the spinner. If we run the application, you can see that the spinner steps through
predefined values set in its model. You can set these to include negative numbers as well.
Clicking on Model you see that NetBeans defines presets for date, lists, and number values.
Let's use numbers, and we'll set the initial value to 1, the minimum value to 1, and the maximum to 10,
keep the step size at 1. Now let's have another look. (Running)
The spinner steps through our predefined range of numbers, but how do we get these values and use them?
We right-click on the spinner, select Events, Change, and stateChanged.
This is triggered obviously when the spinner's state changes. The method jSpinner1StateChanged is created
and passed an event object. We'll need to cast that object to a JSpinner type.
Then we can get the value. (Working) I could get this value as an integer, or, in this case, I'm going to
use a string. (Typing) Adding the toString method, we can just print this out to the console. (Working)
There's an error flagged here because we need to add the import for JSpinner class.
Let's check it out. (Working) Now the values print to the console.
Of course you would likely do something more useful with these values.
So let's make a little room and add a slider. Sliders are very similar, but you cannot see the immediate output
displayed like the spinner. (Working) Some of the nice features of a slider are that you can select the
property paintTicks. (Working) Then select majorTickSpacing, which we'll set to 10, and minorTickSpacing,
which we'll set to 2. Then when you select paintLabels, and we have very nice feedback for the user. (Working)
We still don't have any displayed output here, but instead of just printing these values out to the console
again, let's do something more fun. Let's go ahead and add a progress bar. (Working)
It's already set for the minimum and maximum values of 0 to 100, so we'll leave that.
A nice feature of progress bars is the property called stringPainted, which displays the percentage of
completion you are likely already familiar with seeing. (Working)
So now let's add the code. Right-click the slider and select Events, Changed, stateChanged, same as before.
It created a method called jSlider1StateChanged. The code will be almost the same as before, but this time we'll
cast it to JSlider. And this time I want the integer value. (Working)
Let me get this window out of the way. (Typing) I could use this value to set the value of the progress bar
because it looks for an integer. We have to import the JSlider class, and let's check it out.
Now the value outputted from the slider is used as an input for the progress bar. (Working)
Now the slider's initial value was set for 50. In this case, I'd rather change that to 0. (Working)
Well, let's have another look. Obviously you could use another more practical input value to display in the
progress bar in a real life situation. Now you have a very good understanding of the capabilities of spinners,
sliders, and progress bars. Next, we'll explore tables and trees.