It's time to explore tables and trees. We won't have enough space to add these to our current form,
so let's create a new project. First, let's close out this window.
Then, as we've done before, go to File, New Project, Java Application.
Let's call it TableTreeProject. Make sure Create Main Class is deselected.
Then right-click on the project, New, JFrame Form. Let's call it TableTreeGUI and package name com.Pluralsight.
(Working) Okay, now we can make the frame large enough for our examples.
So first, let's drag a table onto the form. The table's default size is four columns and four rows.
We'll just stick with that for now. Notice that the table is also wrapped in a scroll pane as you can see in
the inspector pane. Now, if we click on model, we can edit the names and types of the columns.
Let's call the first one First Name, and we'll make it a string, the next one Last Name, also a string,
then Age, and let's make that an integer. And lastly, let's call this Opt In and make it a Boolean.
We have option here of making the table cells editable by the user or not inserting, deleting, or moving columns
and changing the row and column count. If we click on the Default Values tab, we can enter in default values
in the table cells. Of course it's quite likely that if you are including a table in a form you're going to
be displaying data from a database. In a later module, we will be binding data to a table.
For now, we are going to just explore the basics and keep it simple.
We also have options here for inserting, deleting, and moving columns and rows.
Now, if we run this, (Working) you can see our table appears as you would expect.
The table cells are editable by the user. (Working) I can also edit the model by right-clicking and selecting
Table Contents. Here I can deselect the editable property. I can change table cell data, or edit the column's
names and types. (Working) Let's have a look at the tree. (Working)
Let's resize it a bit. The default comes loaded with sample data.
We'll just use that for our example. The tree is also wrapped in a scroll pane.
Let's run it and see what it does. You can expand each of the nodes and select one or multiple selections.
Let's take a look at the model for a moment. You can set the nodes and sub-nodes over here on the left.
The top level has no space before the text. The next sublevel has one space, and the next sublevel has two spaces.
You can also bind data to a tree. Tables and trees are very powerful GUI components and can also be a little
bit more complex. There are events associated with both, but we will not dive into that code at this time.
As I mentioned, in an upcoming module we will bind a database to a table for a more real world example.