By now, you have quite a lot of knowledge of Swing and should be able to build a very nice GUI application,
but most applications require some kind of interaction with a database.
Let's use our existing GUI form ContactsTableGUI to display the data.
We can add an Insert button here at the bottom to insert records, then we can allow the user to simply click
on a row of the table, which will pop up our GridBagGUI form to allow updating or deleting records.
I have written a class called DBManager that will do most of the work and we will step through that code to
familiarize you with it first, then move on to controlling it from the GUI classes.
In the last module, I neglected to add the derbyclient.jar directly into the application.
This jar is necessary to provide network communication with the Java DB server.
To add it, right-click the GridBagProject and select Properties, then click Libraries, then Add JAR/Folder.
You will need to point to the directory where derbyclient.jar lives.
If you use the Java DB included in the JDK installation, it lives in the jdk folder /db/lib.
Click on the derbyclient.jar and click OK, then click OK once again.
Now let's look at the DBManager class. I'm using the Java Persistence API, or JPA, to make interaction with
the database much easier. JPA is an Object Relational Mapping, or ORM, meaning that you as a developer only
need to deal with objects to interact with a database and don't need to use SQL.
We're actually already using JPA in the Contacts entity bean we generated earlier, so this is a natural extension.
So first of all, it's necessary to import these three classes to use JPA - the EntityManager,
the EntityManagerFactory, and Persistence. I created variables here for an EntityManagerFactory and an EntityManager.
So in the default constructor for DBManager, I created an instance of EntityManagerFactory,
then created an instance of EntityManager. Every time we perform an insert on the database,
this constructor will be called first, then when the insert is complete, we will call the Close method to
clean up those instances. I have a second constructor here to be used when we want to either update or
delete a record in the database. This constructor takes a Contacts bean object as an argument,
which contains the record we want to either update or delete. Next is an Insert method we will use to create
a new record in the database. When the user fills out the form, we will assign each of the field's first
name, last name, street, and city to an instance of the Contacts bean.
Then JPA just uses that object to persist in the database, and creates a new row.
Not much code necessary. Next, we'll need this findById method.
When the user clicks on a row in the contacts table, we will need to find that record and display its properties
in the GUI form. Then the user will have two options, either update or delete the record.
Again, the form will pass a Contacts object with those values either to the Update or Delete methods here.
JPA may be a new concept to some of you, but I think you can see that it is very easy for the developer to
write methods to interact with the database, and that's the whole point.
You may have heard of other object relational mapping systems, such as Hibernate or TopLink.
JPA is a subset of these and several others. Now there's one more thing we'll need to take care of.
As I mentioned, the Contacts entity bean already makes use of JPA, but we'll need to make a few alterations.
So let's open the Contacts class and have a look. As you see, some of the persistence classes are already imported.
One problem we're going to have is that when we previously entered records manually into the database,
we just entered a primary key directly. Now that we are using code to insert records, we will need some kind of
number generator to generate unique primary key values. No worries, JPA and Java DB already have one included.
JPA makes use of a type of code in entity beans called annotations.
Here you see this class being declared as an Entity with this annotation.
To create a number sequence generator, we will need to add another annotation on the next line,
@SequenceGenerator name=seq initialValue=5. We already have four records in the database using primary keys
one through four, so this will start counting at five and above.
We have an error flag here because we need to add the import for a sequence generator.
Only one more thing to do. We'll need to replace these two annotations here with a new one,
@GeneratedValue strategy=GenerationType.SEQUENCE, generator=seq.
This ensures that the ID field is auto-generated. We'll need to add imports for both generated value and
generated type, and that's all there is to it. All we need to do now is alter our GUI classes a bit.