Okay, let's fix the GUI to call our database code. To make life a little easier, let's first rename the four
text fields we'll be using, First Name, Last Name, Street, and City.
In the interest of time, we are not going to include the rest of the fields.
So right-click the First Name text field, and select Change Variable Name, and call it firstNameField.
Then right-click the Last Name field, and call it lastNameField, then right-click the Street field,
call it streetField, and right-click the City field, and call it cityField.
This GUI, GridBagGUI it's called, will pop up whenever we want the user to either insert, update, or delete a record.
The main window of our application is still a contacts table GUI, the one displaying the table data,
so we'll want to change the JFrame property of the GridBagGUI defaultCloseOperation property to DISPOSE
just as we did earlier when we created the About window. Do you remember that?
So now, when this window closes, it will not exit the entire application altogether.
Oh, one last thing. These three buttons should now be called Insert, Update, and Delete, so we'll need to
rename them and let's change the variable names while we're at it.
Right-click, Edit Text, type Insert. Then right-click, Change Variable Name to insertButton.
Right-click, Edit Text, and type Update. Right-click, Change Variable Name to updateButton.
Right-click, Edit Text, call it Delete. Right-click it, change its name to deleteButton.
For now, let's go over to the ContactsTableGUI and add what we need there.
Let's stretch out the JFrame to make room for a new button. Drag a button down here, change its text to Add Contact,
and change its variable name to addContactButton. Now let's right-click the button and create an
actionPerformed event for it. Here is where we can create the GridBagGUI form, so the user can enter the new data.
So as we did before for the About GUI in a previous module, we type new GridBagGUI.setVisible true.
Now let's try it. The application starts up with the contacts table as the default, click the Add Contact
button, and the GridBagGUI form appears. Next, we'll add our insert code.