When the user is entering a new record, it doesn't really make much sense for the Update and Delete buttons
to be visible. No problem. As you may recall, we used two different constructors to create the GridBagGUI window.
The first one here is the default and is called when we want to insert a record, so here we can type
updateButton.setVisible false and deleteButton.setVisible false.
Just to ensure we cover all our bases, let's play it safe and make sure that the Insert button is visible,
so we type insertButton.setVisible true. Now this next constructor is called for update and delete operations.
We don't want the Insert button and we do want the Update and Delete buttons, so let's paste the code and change
insert to false, update and delete to true. One last thing is necessary to make our Insert button work,
so right-click and select Action, actionPerformed. First, we'll need to create an instance of the Contacts
object, then assign the text fields from the form to its properties.
So Contacts c = new Contacts. C.setFirstname firstNameField.getText.
Then c.setLastname = lastNameField.getText, and c.setStreet streetField.getText, and lastly,
c.setCity = cityField.getText. Now to store our object in the database, we just create an instance of DBManager,
DBManager dbm = new DBManager and call its Insert method passing our Contacts object as a parameter,
dbm.insert c, then clean up the DBManager with the Close method.
Then of course the form window should close when we're done, so we can do that with setVisible false and dispose.
Now before we run it, we should start the DB server and connect to the database, so click the Services tab,
right-click Java Database, and select Start Server, then click the connection and select Connect.
Now let's run the application. Click on the Add Contact button and our form appears.
Only the Insert button is visible. Type in some data, first name, last name, street, and city, then click Insert.
The form window closes and oh, we have a problem here. The contacts table isn't updating with the new record.
Although there are solutions to forcing the table to refresh with the new data, none of them are actually very
easy to implement. In our case here, there is one simple work-around.
When the Add Contact button is clicked and the GridBagGUI form is generated, we can close the contacts table
window temporarily. Then when the user clicks the Insert button, we can regenerate the ContactsTableGUI and
it will appear with the new data. So first, let's move over to the ContactsTableGUI,
addContactButtonActionPerformed method, and add code to close that window.
We can just type setVisible false and dispose. Now back to the GridBagGUI's insertButtonActionPerformed
method and add new ContactTableGUI.setVisible true. Now this is not an ideal way of dealing with this issue,
but it does work for our purposes without getting overly complex.
Okay, let's run it once again. (Running) Click Add Contact and the contacts table closes.
Enter first name, last name, street, and city, click Insert, and the contacts table opens again showing our new data.
Next, we will cover update and delete.