I hope you're still with me as we dive into issues that are a bit more complex.
Realistically, up until now, most solutions have been taken care of with just a few lines of code.
I'm afraid that now we're going to move into a little more advanced coding and it may be a little challenging
for some of you, but please bear with me, I'll explain the code as best possible and it'll be a valuable tool
you can use in the future. Now let's move forward and talk about updating or deleting records in our table.
From the user's standpoint, it would be nice if he or she could simply click on a row in our contacts table
and have that row's data appear in the GridBagGUI's form for the user to then update or delete.
To make this happen, we can use the ListSelectionListener that fires an event called valueChanged whenever
a table row is clicked upon. Now I'm not going to make you watch me type all this code, so I've already written
it and we'll just go over it together. As you can see I implemented the ListSelectionListener interface.
In the ContactsTableGUI constructor, we are creating a ListSelectionModel based upon our table,
which is still called jTable1, and adding the listener. Now whenever a row of the table is clicked,
this method, valueChanged, will be called. I'm using the getValueIsAdjusting method we used once before to
make sure only the mouseDown event is triggered from the click and not both mouseDown and mouseUp.
Here, I look at the TableModel to figure out which row was clicked and it returns the value of that row's
primary key, the ID field. Now I can call the findById method of our DBManager class, which returns a Contacts
bean loaded with that data. Then we call the DBManager.close method.
I then call the constructor of the GridBagGUI's window passing the Contacts bean it will use to populate the
fields of the form. And of course, we will have to also close the ContactsTable window just as we did with insert.
Are you still with me? A little bit complex, but a useful feature that you may be able to use in the future.
So let's look now at the GridBagGUI constructor and you see how it uses the properties of the Contacts bean
to populate the text fields. Now I had to add something extra here.
Before, I was passing the information in the Contacts bean directly to the form, then passing that information
in another Contacts bean to the Update or Delete method. The problem with that is that the form doesn't
display the ID field, so it gets lost in the process. So to fix that, I created a local copy of the Contacts
bean, which does contain the ID field, and we use that when updating or deleting.
I told you this was going to be a little more complicated. Let's run it and see what happens.
Click on a row in the table, and voila! The form appears filled with that row's data.
Now we just need to add an actionPerformed method to our Update button.
To save time, I've already done this and written the code. In this method, first we use the local copy of the
Contacts bean containing the ID field, then we set each of its other values to the new information that was
possibly changed in the form, then we create an instance of DBManager and call its Update method passing the
Contacts bean as an argument. And we call DBmanager.close to clean up and we recreated the ContactsTable
window and close this one. Let's try it out. Click a table row, change some info here, and click Update.
Our data has changed in the table. Everything is already in place to also delete a record, except we need to
create the Delete button's actionPerformed method. I've already done this as well.
In this case, all we need to do is create an instance of DBManager and call its Delete method passing the
Contacts bean as an argument, and then call DBManager.close. Then of course dealing with the closing and
opening of the windows as before. It was necessary to make a change to the DBManager's Delete method.
Let's have a look and I'll explain. Before, I was just passing the Contacts bean and calling the EntityManager's
Remove method. It is necessary to first find that record then remove it.
An error was appearing initially because the two Contacts beans were in different contexts.
This is an issue that is too involved to explain here, but nevertheless the code works now because the two
Contacts beans are in the same context. These are the sorts of issues that pop up in the world of software engineering.
If it were easy, everyone would do it. Let's try this now. Click a row, the record appears in the form.
Actually, the user could alter the fields here, but it won't matter if we click the Delete button.
You could also add an Are you sure dialog here, but for now, we're just going to click Delete and you see our
record is gone. I hope all this wasn't too complex. Nevertheless, this is knowledge you now have and will
surely need as an application developer.