Well now you have built an application that interacts with the database.
Using the GUI windows we built previously, you learned to insert, update, and delete records in a database table.
Although we had to actually write some code to do so, you learned some valuable techniques.
As a bonus,
you had an introduction to the Java Persistence API and learned how that makes the developer's job somewhat
easier using its EntityManager methods.
You learned about annotations and how to use them to create a unique primary key generator.
You learned how to set the visibility of buttons in a window to suit the application's needs.
You learned how to create and close windows easily. You learned how to
match text fields in a form to a Java entity bean, then use that object with the EntityManager.
You learned how to use the ListSelectionListener interface to listen for mouse events on a JTable,
then pass that row's data to a GUI window's text fields.
There are many different ways to code to interact with a database.
How would you go about it? At least now, you have a strong foundation of how to build the GUI interface.