There's an amazing tool in NetBeans called the GridBag Customizer.
It makes the process of building a complex GUI very easy and painless.
The tool uses a Swing layout called
GridBagLayout, which is probably the most powerful layout Swing offers, yet it can be quite complex to code by hand.
GridBagLayout is basically the same as an HTML table with rows and columns.
Components within each cell can span rows or columns. Components can anchor into different locations within
each cell, and components can dictate their own spacing within each cell.
I've already built a new project called GridBagProject and built a basic GUI with a few labels, text fields,
buttons, and a combo box. I've done no layout here whatsoever, just placed the components all in a row.
We'll use the GridBag Customizer for all of the layout. To begin, we'll need to right-click the JFrame and
Set Layout to Grid Bag Layout first. Then we can right-click the JFrame once again and select Customize Layout.
This will bring up the customizer. At first glance, this thing looks like it could fly a rocket ship,
but it's really pretty easy to use. You see our components on the right and the numbered rows and columns of the layout.
There is a toolbar at the top of the window with several functions we'll get to later, and on the left,
if we select a component, is the property editor for layout values of each component.
These values can either be set directly in the area at the bottom or adjusted manually with the arrows in the above section.
So let's try to make something out of our GUI. Let's start by dragging the Last Name label to the row below,
which is automatically created, then the text field, the Street label, it's text field, the Browse button,
the City label, it's text field and another Browse button, the State label, and lastly the combo box.
Now let's select the First and Last Name text fields and drag their boundaries so that they span two columns.
Then set their Fill property to Horizontal so that they fill the cells completely.
Let's then select the Street and City text fields and do the same.
Now we have a lot of extra columns here that we don't need, so let's right-click and select Delete Column for
each of them. (Working) I'm going to leave the 3 column for future use.
There's a button in the toolbar that enables us to preview the design quite easily.
It's right here. Let's have a look. It looks okay, but if I stretch the window you see that all of the
components remain their original size and stay centered in the JFrame.
We can fix that with a property called Weight.
There are weight parameters for X and Y, X representing row and Y representing column.
I want the text fields to stretch along with the window, so let's select all of them, Ctrl+Click,
and change their Weight X property value to 1.0. Weights are described with values between 0 and 1.
Now let's preview the application again, and the text fields stretch appropriately.
Now here's another problem. The State combo box sort of floats out to the center, and also you can see that
the labels aren't really aligned very well on the left here. We can fix all this with the Anchor property.
So let's select all of those, then set the Anchor property to Line Start and see how that works.
Let's preview it. Now the labels are aligned, and the combo box stays where it should.
Now our application still looks a bit cramped. We could do with a bit of spacing.
So let's select all of the components (Working) and select the ellipsis next to the Insets property.
Here we can add spacing to any side of the components. Let's add 5 pixels on the top and left.
I could alternatively use the Insets arrows to manually change these values as well.
Let's preview it once again. Now the components have a little more breathing room.
Next we'll move on to some more advanced techniques. Now what if we want to add some extra components to our application?