It's easy to do in the GridBag Customizer, so right-click and select Customize Layout.
Now I want to add phone numbers to this application. Things might look better if we label and separate these
sections as well. Adding panels might be too complex at this point, but we can easily add a label and a separator.
So first we'll need to right-click the first row and select Insert Row Before to make some room for these new components.
Then we can right-click the first cell and select Add Component, Swing Containers, Label.
Then the next cell, Add Components, Swing Controls, Separator, and let's stretch that to span over two columns.
Then right-click the fifth row and select Insert Row After. Then let's add another label for the phone
number section and then another separator and also stretch that across two columns.
Now let's add some phone number labels and fields. Right-click, Insert Row After, Add Components, Label.
Add Component, Text Field. That one could be for home number. And now add another for the work number,
then another for a cell number. (Working) And let's make a fourth for a Skype number.
Now we are unable to change the actual component properties here, so we'll have to go back to the Design area
to do that. Let's change this label to Contact and set it to Bold, and this label to Phone and also to Bold.
Let's change the first label for Home, then the next to Work, the next to Cell, and the last to Skype.
Let's empty the text within the text fields too. They shrink, but no worries, we have layout tools for that.
Okay, we have some layout properties to edit. Start the customizer again, but first let's set the text fields
to Horizontal fill and stretch them over two columns. Let's give all of our new components a little extra
space with the Insets property, (Working) the same as the others, five on the top and left.
While we're at it, let's anchor them all to Line Start. Time to preview what we've done.
Stretching the application seems to work well, but what if we want to redesign a bit?
That's easy to do. The number 3 column seems to have disappeared, so let's add that again, and let's insert
a final row here as well, then add two buttons. It might look nicer if we move the Cell and Skype phone
numbers, so first let's make all of the text fields only one column.
Now we have space to move the Cell and Skype numbers up here. Now we have too many rows, so we can delete those.
And now we can stretch the name fields over three columns, move the Browse buttons over, and stretch City
and State as well. Oh, also the separators need stretching. The Cell and Skype labels might look better if
we align them to the right using the Anchor property. We select Line End.
And the buttons down here also are a little cramped, so let's increase the insets for them. (Working)
All the components above could do with some space on the right, so let's select them and increase the insets.
Now that looks pretty good. Let's preview it and stretch it. Oh, the phone fields don't stretch.
Do you remember which property fixes that? Set the Weight X property to 1.0, and we'll be good.
Let's try it. Now that all looks great. Next, we'll explore Sub Containers.