You may have noticed a few weird things as we stretched the application previously.
The Browse buttons didn't stay put, and the buttons on the bottom here didn't stay together either.
We can fix that by creating something called Sub Containers. So first, let's select the Browse and Street
text field, right-click, and select Enclose in Container. This actually encloses them in a JPanel.
Let's do the same for City and Browse and also again for the buttons along the bottom here.
Now when we stretch the application, things stay where they should.
Now we can't select these buttons any longer. Instead, the JPanel is selected.
No problem. Now all we have to do is right-click and select Design This Container.
Sub Container opens. Let's add another button. Right-click, Insert Column After, right-click the new cell
Add Component Button. Now to return to the parent container, all we have to do is right-click and select
Design Parent Container. Now we haven't changed the names of these buttons yet, so let's return to the Design
area and do so. Right-click, Edit Text, and call this one OK. The next one, Cancel, and the last one, Help.
Now let's go back to the customizer (Working) and then design the button container.
Let's select all three buttons and adjust the insets a bit. (Working)
That's good. Now back to the parent container and preview it. Now everything holds together much better.