NetBeans offers a powerful tool called the Beans Binding Library that is capable of binding values either
between different components or between a component and a database.
These values are automatically kept in sync, all requiring only a few lines of code.
Let's start with a simple example that binds the properties of two components.
One of the components will be the source, and the other will be the target.
A good example might be a JSlider providing its value to be displayed in a JLabel.
So I've built a new project called BindProject with a class BindGUI containing a JSlider and a JLabel,
which I have left with the default names jSlider1 and jLabel1. Let's make the label's font bigger and bold.
To bind these, all we have to do is right-click the label, select Bind and the target property we would like to change.
Let's choose its text property. The binding source, of course, will be jSlider1, and the value we would expect
the slider to output is an integer, so we select the value int.
As you see, the label's text has already changed to 0, which is the initial value of the slider.
That's all there is to it. Now let's run it, and you see that the label's text is in sync with the output
value of the slider.