To demonstrate how to bind data from a component to a database,
first we need a database. Databases are easily set up and configured in the NetBeans Integrated Development Environment.
Any sort of database could be used, but we are going to use a database called Java DB that is included with
the GlassFish Application Server installation and also in the JDK 6 or later.
All that you need should already be in the JDK that you downloaded earlier.
You can check your JDK to see if it's there. Java DB was an open source project originally called Apache Derby,
so if you expand your jdk folder to the db folder, then the lib folder, you should see the derbyclient.jar and so on.
For some reason if it's not there, you can download and extract it to your drive.
Oracle's website is a little confusing, so I recommend this one for an easy install.
It's java-db.updatestar.com. Download it, and then extract it to your drive.
First, your Java DB must be registered in NetBeans, so click the Services tab here, expand Databases,
then right-click Java DB and choose Properties. Here you must point to your Java DB installation directory
and also choose the location where the newly created databases will live.
Mine points to the db folder of my jdk installation. You can use the default for the other location and click OK.
Now right-click the Java DB, and choose Start Server. You should see the progress logged in the console window below.
Right-click Java DB once again, and choose Create Database. Type contact as the database name.
Type nbuser as the username and password. Then click OK. You can see that the database was created,
and down here is the database connection, which is currently not connected denoted by this broken icon.
So to connect to the new database, right-click on the connection and choose Connect.
Now the icon is no longer broken. Now let's give the connection a more convenient name.
Right-click the connection once again and choose Rename. Type in ContactDB and click OK.
There are two methods for creating tables in our new database. You can type SQL directly into the SQL editor
if you wish. Right-click the connection and choose Execute Command.
Type in the SQL in the window. Then click the Run SQL button here at the top.
An easier method though, is to use the create table dialog, so let's close the SQL editor window.
To use the create table dialog, expand the ContactDB connection node, and you will see several schemas listed.
For this example, you will use only the NBUSER schema, so right-click it and choose Set as Default Schema.
Expand the NBUSER node, and you'll see three folders. Right-click the Tables folder and choose Create Table.
Let's call this table CONTACTS, all caps. Click Add column, and let's name it id for our primary key and
make it of type INTEGER. Select Primary key, and also Index and Unique will automatically be selected.
Click OK. Just a few more columns for an example. Let's click Add column again, call this one firstname,
and its type is VARCHAR, which is a string with the size of say 20 characters.
Check Null as its constraint so that if no data is entered a null value will be displayed.
Let's do the same again for lastname, VARCHAR, size 20, and Null.
Just two more columns. Add column, call it street, VARCHAR, and let's allow 30 characters for this and Null.
One last column, Add column, call it city, VARCHAR, size 20, and Null.
Now click OK to create the table. Expand the CONTACTS table node, and you'll see the new columns listed.
We have a table, but no data in it. We could add data by right-clicking the CONTACTS DB and choosing Execute
Command, but there's an easier way. Choose View Data. Our table's empty, so click the Insert Records button
here, and we can directly type in our data. The first column shows an item number.
Let's use the same for our ID, so number 1, FIRSTNAME John, LASTNAME Doe, STREET 1234 Main St., and CITY Anytown.
Let's add another row, ID 2, FIRSTNAME Jane, LASTNAME Smith, STREET 4321 Maple, CITY Cleveland.
Click Add Row, ID 3, Joe, Jones, 1111 Netbeans, and Des Moines.
Just one more. Add Row, ID 4, Mary, Berry, 21 Jump St., and Paris.
That should be enough. Click OK. You see our data listed in the view data table here.
That's it. We've easily created a database for our following example.
When you are finished with NetBeans, before closing, you should Disconnect from CONTACTS and Stop Server on the JavaDB.
You already know how to restart and reconnect next time you open.