Let's use our new contact database and display its data in a table.
We already have a contact form we built earlier that matches some of the fields in the GridBagProject.
To save time, we've only used four of these fields. So let's use the GridBagProject.
We will need to create an entity bean to represent the data in the contacts database.
It's easy to create. Right-click the GridBagProject, select New and Other, then Persistence, then Entity
Classes from Database. In the database connection list, you should see the ContactDB listed here.
If you don't, did you remember to start the server and connect to the database?
Select ContactDB, and you will see a list of available tables here.
There's our CONTACTS table. Select CONTACTS and click Add. Then click Next.
Make sure these checkboxes are all selected. Then click Finish.
A new class is generated here called Contacts.java. If you are familiar with Java, you will recognize this
as a Java bean with getter and setter methods for each of our columns in the table.
Now we're going to need a Swing table to display our data. Let's create a new JFrame in the GridBagProject
and call it ContactsTableGUI in the com.Pluralsight package. Drag a JTable into the design area, resize it a
bit, right-click it, and select Bind elements. Then click Import Data to Form.
Choose ContactDB as the connection, and CONTACTS should be displayed as the table.
Click OK. We see the list of columns here. We may not want to display the id, so let's click it and move it
to the left column. The other columns are in reverse order here for some reason, but we can move them up and
down to whichever order we wish. Then click OK. There's our table.
Run it. We now have two GUIs to choose from, so click this one, and set it to the default.
Our table data is displayed in the JTable now.