You have just learned about the Beans Binding Library provided in NetBeans and used it to bind the properties
from component to component and from a component to a database table.
You learned to bind the property of a
target component to a source component. You learned how to set up and
configure a Java DB Database in the NetBeans Services window. You learned how to start the database server,
create a database,
and connect to it. You learned how to use the
Create Table dialog
and add columns to a table.
You learned how to add data directly into a database table without even using SQL.
You learned how to create an entity bean to represent data in the database table.
Then you learned how to bind a database table to a JTable component.
You've learned the basics of a very powerful tool that makes interacting with a database quite easy.