To understand Swing, you need to gain a basic understanding of containers.
Containers in Swing are used to group components together. Each container can set a different sort of layout
manager for its component. Containers include
JFrame, JWindow, JDialog, JPanel, JInternalFrame, and JApplet. Applets are programs designed to be viewed
within a web browser. We will not spend time with them, and instead focus on other containers.
The containers JFrame, JWindow, JDialog, and JInternalFrame all contain an instance of a class called JRootPane.
JRootPane is a container that also contains a component called JLayeredPane, which includes the components
JMenuBar and a contentPane. JLayeredPane consists of these layers,
allowing components to be overlapped. At the bottom is the Frame_Content_Layer, which contains the JMenuBar
and the contentPane. Next, is the Default_Layer where most components are added.
Then the Palette_Layer where floating toolbars or palettes can be added.
Next, the Modal_Layer or Modal pop-up windows; then the PopUp_Layer for pop-ups and tooltips.
Lastly, the Drag_Layer for objects dragged from outside the application.
We're only covering the basics of containers here, but it will give you the concepts necessary to understand
what we are going to explore. Let's move on and look at each of the containers.