The first containers we are going to look at are also the simplest, JPanels.
JPanel actually extends component, so it uses all the common properties of components we have already explored.
To demonstrate, let's use our SwingComponentProject. Now of course I can drag a new JPanel onto the design
area, but since all my components are already present, I can select each set of components I choose to enclose
in a JPanel, right-click, and choose Enclose In Panel. As I mentioned, panels have all the common properties
of other components, such as background and foreground colors, borders, etc.
Mostly JPanels are useful for dividing sections of your application making the design cleaner and more
intuitive for the user. We haven't discussed layouts specifically, but here's a property for applying specific
layouts to each panel. Please explore layouts further if you wish.
Now the most common and useful property of a panel is the border property.
Let's select Border and then Titled Border and add a title called Personal Info and change the font to Arial,
Bold, 12, and the border type to Etched. (Working) Let's run the application and see what it looks like.
I think you'll agree that panels can clean up the look of your application dramatically.
Now to clean up this further, I might like to lose the Bio label here and instead enclose the text area in a
Titled Border JPanel and title it Bio. So Enclose In Panel, resize the panel, resize the text area a bit.
We'll change the Panel property to Titled Border, add the title Bio, change the font, and make sure it's the Etched Border.
I might also enclose these radio buttons as well and call them Marital Status.
So again Enclose In Panel, resize the panel, change the border to Titled Border once again, add the title
Marital Status, change the font, and again make sure it's the Etched Border.
Now, let's run it and see what it looks like. (Running) Please feel free to play around and design your own version.