Okay, let's explore scroll panes. Scroll panes are somewhat self-explanatory.
As you have seen, NetBeans intuitively encloses components in scroll panes, such as text areas, lists, and so on.
You can also add scroll panes manually in much the same way as we did with JPanels or use the function,
Enclose In Scroll Pane, although some components are not allowed to be directly enclosed in a scroll pane.
You can though place components on a JPanel first and then enclose the JPanel in a scroll pane.
You can then decide how to set the appearance of both the vertical and horizontal scroll bars using the
properties horizontalScrollBarPolicy and verticalScrollBarPolicy.
You can choose AS_NEEDED, and they will appear when necessary. Or you can choose ALWAYS, and they will
always be visible. You can actually choose NEVER, but I'm not quite sure why you would add a scroll pane and
never have the scroll bars appear. Maybe you can tell me why. Another odd thing I haven't figured out,
there is a Scroll Bar component over here, but I don't know what you would ever do with it.
Please enlighten me if you have figured it out. (Working) Let's run the application and see how the scroll panel appears. (Working)