The next container we'll explore is the Split Pane. You have probably seen split panes used before
in applications. A split pane has two distinct resizable sections split either horizontally or vertically.
Example uses might be two text files that need to be compared or possibly a representation of a file structure.
You can place anything in either side of the pane, possibly buttons in one pane and a result in the other.
I have created a new project with a class called PlaygroundGUI so we can explore.
Let's drag a split pane into the design area and have a look. Now this requires some explanation.
The split pane in NetBeans defaults to two buttons, but they don't show up as components, a little confusing.
The buttons are only placeholders and will disappear once we drag a JPanel into each side.
Then we can add any components we wish. I want to add text areas to each pane.
I could try to drag text areas into each pane of the split pane and try to align the edges, but there is an easier way.
If I first drag two text areas into the design, (Working) then I can select them both, right-click, Enclose In,
Split Pane, and that's a lot easier. Notice NetBeans also encloses these in scroll panes automatically.
Let's set each text area to lineWrap and wrapStyleWord and place some default text as well. (Working)
Let's run it. The user can drag the divider back and forth as necessary.
You can set the initial location of the divider with the dividerLocation property.
The default position is designated as -1, but if you want to move it elsewhere the number value is actually in pixels.
(Working) You can also change the dividerSize property. That's also in pixels. (Working)
You can of course set the divider to VERTICAL_SPLIT here in the orientation property as well. (Working)
An additional feature can be enabled with the oneTouchExpandable property.
When enabled, two small arrows appear within the divider. (Working)
Clicking on one expands to the maximum. Clicking the other returns to default and then maximum the other way.
That's JSplit panes. You've learned the basic features. Please explore more with other components as well.