Let's learn about tabbed panes next. Let's drag a Tabbed Pane into the design area.
If we want to see defined edges around the pane, we'll need a border.
I like the Soft Bevel Border for this. Now the tabbed pane all by itself doesn't look like much.
To add tabs, you must drag JPanels into the tabbed pane for each tab.
When the border of the tabbed pane changes to dashed lines, then you can drop the panel in.
You can of course place any sort of components into each tab. Let's add some labels to each just for
demonstration purposes. It is also possible to nest tabbed panes.
Select the tabbed pane, right-click, and select Enclose In Tabbed Pane.
That will add a tab. To add another tab, right-click, Add From Palette, Swing Containers, Tabbed Pane.
Now to change the name of a tab, right-click, and go to Edit Text.
You can use the tabPlacement property to position the tabs TOP, BOTTOM, LEFT, or RIGHT.
You can also order the tabs using the selectedIndex property. The index counts from 0, so the first tab is
numbered 0, the next 1, and so on, 0 being the default. Let's have a look at the application. (Working)
Oops, I forgot to add a border to the outer tabbed panes. Let's try again. (Working)
You have learned the basics of tabbed panes now. I think you'll agree they're rather easy to implement.