Now let's explore layered panes. Now you might remember our discussion earlier about the various layers of
the Root Pane. Layered panes take advantage of these so that layers of components can be painted on top of
each other and easily set to either visible or not visible.
Let's drag a layered pane into the design area. (Working) We'll need to add panels to the pane allowing the
addition of components as well if you wish. For this example though, let's just color each panel so we can
see what's going on. The first panel I drag is going to be in the topmost layer.
The next will be under that, and the next under that and so on. (Working)
Now to make a useful example, we'll need to write a small bit of code.
It will make more sense if we name each panel first. (Working)
So let's control the visibility of the panels with buttons. I need to add four buttons, one for each panel. (Working)
I don't need to waste time naming these buttons for now. Let's use the first button to make the red panel
visible and the others invisible, so we use the actionPerformed method to control this.
I can type in redPanel.setVisible and set it to true, and I'll set the others to false. (Typing)
Now I can copy and paste this to save time. (Working) Here we'll make only the blue panel visible, (Working)
here we'll make the green visible, (Working) and here the yellow one visible. (Working)
Now let's try it. (Working) You've learned the basics of layered panes.
Do you have any idea about how you might use them?