Next, we're going to explore toolbars. Toolbars can be oriented vertically or horizontally.
The typical toolbar contains buttons most often using image icons, something you've probably seen before such
as the cut, copy, and paste buttons. I'm going to use the Swing component GUI we built before because it has
a bit more room. I've already moved the existing components down a bit to make some space, so let's add a
toolbar at the top. (Working) Now to make this function as we want, we'll need to add a panel as well.
And to make this function properly as a floatable toolbar, we'll also need to set the layout to BorderLayout.
This will ensure that the toolbar can be floatable and redocked to the same location.
Now let's add three buttons. The buttons expand to maximum size because of the BorderLayout.
That's okay because we're going to add image icons with the icon property. (Working)
Let's adjust the toolbar to fit our new buttons. Now let's run the application. (Running)
Of course the buttons act like any button you're already familiar with.
Since our toolbar isFloatable property is checked, we can rip the toolbar off the frame and float it in a
variety of locations. The buttons will still perform as usual.
Then when the toolbar is closed, it redocks to its original location.
Now you have mastered toolbars. You can place any sort of component in a toolbar.
How would you use it?