The last containers we're going to learn about are the coolest, I think, Desktop Pane and Internal Frames.
These containers give you the power to build applications that look just like a computer desktop with internal windows.
The best way to teach you about these is just to show you. I've already built a new project called
DesktopProject with a class called DesktopGUI. Let's drag a Desktop Pane into the design area and stretch it
to the maximum. You can change the background color to whatever you like.
Now let's drag an Internal Frame on to the desktop. Not sure why the windows are so tiny by default.
The most important properties of internal frames are iconifiable, maximizable, and resizable.
We'll want to select all of these, and you'll see why in a minute.
And let's give the window a title as well. Let's add a couple more internal frames and duplicate those same
settings once again. (Working) Of course each internal frame can contain any containers or components.
Let's just add a label to each for now. It's time to run it and see what it does.
Check out the cool desktop. Since the internal frames are iconifiable, the minimize button appears in each frame.
And since the maximizable property is set, those buttons appear as well.
There's also a menu on the left with the same options, so I'm able to minimize each frame, and they dock
along the bottom. I can also move the iconified frame, and it will now dock to the new location. (Working)
Whichever frame you select automatically rises to the topmost layer so the frames can overlap.
There's one more property I should mention, and that's the closable property.
Let's select it for the first frame. Now you can see there is an X button allowing that window to close.
Of course you would have to offer an option to find that window once again, possibly a menu, but we'll get to
that soon enough. So now you've learned how to use Desktop Panes along with Internal Frames.