You have learned about the structure and use of Swing containers and how NetBeans makes them easy to design and implement.
You've learned about JRootPane and its elements JLayeredPane containing JMenuBar and contentPane.
You've also learned about the six different layers that JLayeredPane consists of.
You learned to use JPanels to enclose and group other components into sections within your application.
You learned that you can enclose other containers inside a scroll pane.
You learned how to
implement split panes and its properties dividerLocation, dividerSize, and oneTouchExpandable.
You have learned how to create tabs within a tabbed pane and how to next tabbed panes as well.
You've learned the capabilities of JLayeredPane and how to hide or show a layer using the setVisible method.
You now know how to create floatable toolbars within any application.
You've learned how to build a fully-functioning desktop-style application using JDesktopPane and JInternalFrames.
You know how to make JInternalFrames iconifiable, maximizable, resizable, and closable.
Since now you have a good understanding of components and containers, you are already well
on your way to mastering Swing and NetBeans.