Wow, we have covered quite a lot of information. You should now be capable of building nearly any sort of
GUI interface using Swing. You now have learned valuable skills that can
surely increase your worth as a programmer whether you are a beginner or a seasoned developer.
You learned about Swing's structure and capabilities.
You learned about the Model-View-Controller architecture and its benefits.
You learned how to download and use the NetBeans IDE and about many of its powerful features.
Most importantly, you have learned how the NetBeans IDE can make building complex cross-platform GUI
interfaces easy and fast, leaving time for more difficult coding that you will surely need.
You learned the basics of many Swing components including labels, text fields, text areas, buttons,
radio buttons, checkboxes, lists, combo boxes, spinners, sliders, progress bars, tables, and trees.
You learned about Swing containers including panels, scroll panes, split panes, tabbed panes, layered panes,
toolbars, desktop panes, and internal frames. You learned how to
build Swing menus including checkbox menus, radio button menus, submenus, and pop-up menus and how to handle
events from menu selections. You learned how
to create dialogs including the showMessageDialog,
the showInputDialog,
and the showOptionDialog. You learned how to
use File Choosers
and Color Choosers as well. You learned about NetBeans powerful tool,
the GridBag Customizer and how easy it is to build complex GUIs with it.
You learned how to bind properties of a component to another components property.
Then you learned how to set up the Java DB database,
create tables,
and data within it using NetBeans database tools.
You learned how to bind the database table to a JTable to display it.
Finally, you learned how to build
a complete application interacting with a database inserting, update, and deleting records.
You also had an introduction to the Java Persistence API.
You now have quite a lot of valuable tools and an idea about what else you might be able to learn to expand
upon those skills. You may have been wondering how to deploy your application once you've built it within NetBeans.
That's pretty easy to do if you just right-click your project and select Clean and Build.
In the directory structure of where your NetBeans projects are saved, there's a folder called dist for
distribution, and in that folder you will find a double-clickable, executable JAR file that you can distribute
to run your application.