Now that you have learned how to use NetBeans to generate Swing code for you, it would also be a very valuable
skill to learn how to actually hand code Swing yourself.
You're in luck because there is another course here on Pluralsight that teaches exactly that.
I hope you have taken some time along the way to have a
look at the generated code and familiarized yourself with it.
Now there are a few areas of Swing that I did not cover, number one being layouts since NetBeans takes care
of most of that for you, but if you learn to code Swing, you will definitely need to spend time learning
about the various layouts Swing offers and how to use them. Other areas you may want to explore further
include Swing's Undo Management classes, Accessibility classes, or assistive technologies, Print Utilities,
and 2D and 3D drawing features. There are even add-ons for advanced charting and audio as well.
Well I hope you've enjoyed the course and have learned some valuable information.
Until next time.