In this module, we'll explore some fun and interesting features of Swing -
Dialog Windows,
File Choosers,
and Color Choosers.
Let's start with dialog windows. In the Abstract Windows Toolkit, the older version of Swing,
dialogs were dependent upon the native operating system, and coding was a lot more complex.
Now Swing offers the JOptionPane, which we briefly used in our first example application.
JOptionPanes are used when information needs to be displayed to the user briefly, so, for example,
a message window with an OK button. Also, they may be used to acquire some information from the user such as
a username or a password.
Now although NetBeans provides JOptionPanes and dialog components that you can drag into the design area,
I actually find it easier and more practical to build our own with code.
Most often, you're going to be creating these windows programmatically anyhow, and it only takes one line of
code to create a JOptionPane, so it's really easy to do.
JOptionPanes are made up of four elements, some of which may be null values.
First, there's a message, which usually contains textual information.
Second, there is an icon, which indicates which type of message you are displaying.
Third is a data input area allowing the user to enter some sort of value, and now this can be either a text
field, a list, or a combo box. And the fourth are buttons, such as OK or Cancel.
There are three basic formats of JOptionPane.
First, for information only types of messages, you can use the showMessageDialog method.
The second window that gives the user options can be brought up with
the showOptionDialog method. And last, for dialogs requiring user input,
you can use the showInputDialog method. Let's explore these with an example.
Let's use the SwingComponentGUI we previously built. Let's use the buttons in the toolbar to initiate our dialog windows.
So if we double-click jButton2, it will create an ActionPerformed method for our code.
Let's start with a simple message to display information to the user, so I'll type JOptionPane.showMessageDialog.
And you can see here that there are three options with different parameters.
Let's choose the simplest form first, which is this option. It requires two parameters.
First is the parent component. Now this can be used to place the window near a specific component,
but in most cases will be null, which places the dialog centered within the default JFrame.
So let's make the parent component null. The second parameter is for our message, so let's add a string.
How about Have a nice day! Now, of course, we need to add the import for the JOptionPane class, and let's run it.
(Running) We now have an informational dialog with an i icon, our message, and an OK button, which closes the window.
Let's go back to our method and try the next option, which adds a title and a message type. (Typing)
If you read the documentation here, you can see the various options for message type, which can be
ERROR_MESSAGE, INFORMATION_MESSAGE, WARNING_MESSAGE, QUESTION_MESSAGE, or PLAIN_MESSAGE.
Each will automatically contain a corresponding image icon with the exception of PLAIN_MESSAGE, which is no icon.
If you really want to customize your own window, it is also possible to choose and display your own custom image icon.
Let's choose this option without a custom icon. The parent component should be null.
Let's add a message. (Working) Now something isn't right here with the way NetBeans created our parameters.
The next two parameters are title and message type. For some reason this comes up with WIDTH.
Let's just ignore that, and let's type a title, and we'll of course make this a WARNING_MESSAGE from JOptionPane. (Working)
Now let's give it a try. (Running) There, now our title appears, and it displays the warning icon.
Please play around with these further on your own. Now let's explore the second type of JOptionPane using
showOptionDialog. Let's double-click jButton3, (Working) and there's only one option here as you can see.
You can read about the parameters displayed here in the help text, and there's a new parameter called optionType,
which gives options such as YES_NO, YES_NO_CANCEL, and OK_CANCEL.
And again, of course the parameters displayed here are really of no help.
Now since we're going to have several options, the easiest way to deal with this is to create an array of
objects, which will be our selection of strings. Let's create a variable called options, which contains our string array.
(Working) The first parameter in the method is the parent component.
We'll set that to null. Next is the message. (Working) Next, the title for the window. (Working)
And let's choose the option type as YES_NO_CANCEL, (Working) then the message type as QUESTION_MESSAGE,
a null icon, our array of options, and an initial value. Now the showOptionDialog method returns an integer
indicating the user's choice or a closed option value if the user closes the window.
Okay, let's run it. (Running) Our dialog appears with three buttons showing our options.
Now let's try out dialogs that require user input. So let's double-click the jButton4, and this time we'll
use the method showInputDialog. Ah, here we have six options with various parameters.
The simplest option is just a basic message. Let's try that. This method is going to return the user's
input as a string, so let's create a variable called input and type our message, Please enter a value.
Let's run it. (Running) Our dialog displays the question mark icon and has automatically added a text field,
an OK, and a Cancel button. If we type something and hit OK, the value would of course be assigned to our
string called input. Currently, we're not doing anything with that value.
Cancelling the window would return a null value to our input string.
Now let's go back to our method and check out our other options.
The second choice adds the parent component. The next option would place an initial value, a string into the text field.
The next offers the various types of image icons that can be associated and a title.
And the last offers a custom icon, an array of selection values, and an initial value.
Why not? Let's just go for the most complex. Once again, NetBeans doesn't display the correct parameters
here, so I'll just have to remember, so the parent component, null again, our message, a title, the message type,
(Working) an icon, let's just keep it null, our selection values.
Now, here we'll need to create an object array of string values to choose from, so let's create a variable
called options with several string values, then place that into our method. (Working)
And lastly, let's choose Yes as our initial value. The method returns an object, so we need to cast it to a string.
Let's run it. (Running) Now our dialog displays a list with our values, and Yes is initially selected.
There are many variations of dialog windows. Please explore these further on your own.