You're about to learn something very useful. We're going to build a File Chooser and open a file.
Let's get right into it, and I'll show you how it's done. I think it's best if we start a new project for this example.
So let's choose New Project, Java Application, call it FileChooserProject, deselect Create Main Class,
then right-click the project and select New JFrame Form, call the class FileChooserGUI, and the package com.Pluralsight.
Let's make the application larger and add a JMenuBar. We won't need the second menu, so right-click it and Delete.
Now right-click File and Add From Palette, Menu Item. Right-click to Edit Text, and change it to Open.
Might as well double-click the shortcut and make it Ctrl+O. Let's change the variable name to Open.
While we're at it, let's create one more for exit, so right-click File, Add From Palette, Menu Item.
Right-click Edit Text to exit. Double-click the shortcut, and make it Ctrl+Q.
Change the variable name to Exit, as well. We've done this before, so you should be an expert by now.
Double-click the Exit menu item, and it creates the ExitActionPerformed method, and we'll type in system.exit(0)
as we've done before. Before we move on to the File Chooser, let's also add a text area to our application.
Let's stretch it to the max and change its variable name to textArea.
Now here's a great trick. It's time to add the File Chooser, but we don't want to just drag it into the design area.
We want to create it with code from our open menu item. So here we can right-click the Other Components item
in the inspector and select Add From Palette, Swing Windows, File Chooser, and it appears in the inspector.
Right-click to change the variable name to fileChooser. Okay, now we can add our code, so double-click the
Open menu item, and let's paste this code into the method. NetBeans wants us to import the classes that were
added in this code, so click OK. This code creates the fileChooser, reads whichever file you select,
and places it into the text area. One more thing before we try it.
Go back to the Design mode, select the fileChooser, right-click, and select Properties.
Let's add a title to dialogTitle. Let's call it Open Dialog. You can change the initial directory it points
to with the currentDirectory property. I want to change mine to C drive.
You can also see that this option allows OPEN_DIALOG, SAVE_DIALOG, and custom options as well.
Let's leave it as the OPEN_DIALOG for now. Okay, let's close this and run it. (Running)
Now go to the File menu and select Open. The fileChooser is created, pointing to the C drive as I wanted.
We can now open any sort of file here within reason. Of course not everything is going to look beautiful in
our text area. So let's make a change that filters only .txt files.
Exit the application, and select Source view. Just below the import statements here, we'll paste this code in.
You don't have to fully understand this code to use it, but this creates an inner class that limits the file
type to .txt files. I called this class CustomFilter. Now return to Design mode, select the fileChooser,
right-click, select Properties, then click here next to the fileFilter property, then select custom code
and type new CustomFilter. And that should do it. Now let's run it again. (Running)
Click File and Open. Now the fileChooser limits the file types to .txt files.
Obviously you could expand this and create a save dialog for your application as well.
Next, we'll look at color choosers.