You may want to offer users the ability to choose color of components or
fonts within an application. Swing provides the JColorChooser component for this purpose.
The Color Chooser can be created anywhere within an application.
Once again, NetBeans provides a Color Chooser component you can simply drag into the design area or add from
palette to the Other Components item in the inspector, such as we did with the File Chooser.
But as with JOptionPanes, the easiest way to create a Color Chooser is with code.
Only one line of code is necessary. Let's use our FileChooserProject to demonstrate.
First, let's add another menu item to the File menu and call it Set Background.
Double-click to create its ActionPerformed method. Let's type JColorChooser.showDialog.
And, as you can see, there is only one option here, and a method with three simple parameters.
The first is the parent component, the same as we used in JOptionPane, next a title for the chooser window,
and last the initial color to be selected. So let's make the parent component null, add a title,
Please choose a color, and the initial color is a constant of the color object, Color.white.
Now this method returns a color object, so let's add that and call it color.
Now we can use that color result to set the background of our text area.
Just type textArea.setBackground(color). And that's it. Let's run the application and check it out. (Running)
Select the menu item Set Background, and the Color Chooser appears.
Now there are five different panels here with different ways to select colors.
If that is not enough for you, then color choosers can be customized for your specific needs as well.
If we choose a color and click OK, the text area's background is set to that color.
That was pretty easy. How would you use a Color Chooser in an application?