You have learned some very interesting and powerful techniques as we've covered the basics of
JOptionPanes,
File Choosers,
and Color Choosers, all of which are very useful to almost any application.
First, you learned about the four elements of JOptionPanes: message, icon, data input, and buttons.
Then you learned about the three formats of JOptionPanes using versions of the three methods
showMessageDialog,
showOptionDialog,
and showInputDialog. You learned about
the various message types available in JOptionPanes, as well as the option types.
You also learned how to implement a File
Chooser, how to set its properties to point to specific directories, and you were introduced to code that
opens a file and displays it within a text area. You were introduced to code to filter specific
file types within a File Chooser as well. You also learned
of the JColorChooser component and the showDialog method used to create it.
You learned how to use the color object it returns to change the color of almost any component within your application.
Next, you'll learn how to customize the layout of an application more specifically using a tool call the
GridBag Customizer that comes in NetBeans.