Hi. This is Rusty Lowery from Pluralsight. Welcome to Java Swing Development Using NetBeans.
In this course, you're going to learn how to use NetBeans Integrated Development Environment or IDE to
program desktop applications using Java Swing. I think you'll find this process is rather easy to learn,
yet the skills and concepts you will acquire are quite powerful and will increase your skillset as a
programmer in a big way.
I used to program Swing applications manually, but I was blown away when I discovered how easy NetBeans makes
this process in comparison. I assume that you have some familiarity with some sort of programming language,
but most of what we'll be doing here will not require an in-depth understanding of Java, although this
course can also benefit a seasoned programmer.
You will learn how to use the powerful NetBeans GUI builder to quickly develop complex user interfaces with
little effort allowing you more time to build the application logic instead.
First, we'll start with a short introduction to Swing's architecture and features.
Then we'll move on to explore NetBeans and its fantastic GUI builder.
We'll then jump right in and create a fully-functional application to give you a very good idea of just what
NetBeans and Swing can accomplish in a very short period of time.
Then we'll dig deeper into each of Swing's components, containers, menus, and windows and explore what they offer.
Following that, we'll explore a NetBeans tool called GridBag Customizer that is very cool.
It makes the job of customizing your layouts and components very easy, and I think you will begin to really
understand the power NetBeans tools can offer. Lastly, we will move into some more advanced topics,
such as setting up a database to interact with an application and binding data to table views.
NetBeans makes it easy to interface with any sort of database. Our focus will remain mainly on the Swing GUI
view, so I'll be providing the database code. This course is a great
entry point into the world of Java Swing. If you wish to continue your journey further, then you are in luck
because there are more advanced courses covering Swing right here on Pluralsight.
Now let's get started.