Before we get started writing our first application, let's talk for a moment about just exactly what Swing is.
In short, Swing is a powerful, customizable set of graphical components used to create Java desktop applications.
It's a GUI toolkit containing a wide array of graphical components that are independent of the underlying
operating system because they are created at runtime. Now I think the best way to demonstrate Swing's
capabilities is to check out an actual application. Let me show you a great example application provided on
the Java website.
Open up a browser, go to Google, and search for java swingset download.
Click on the first item in the list, SwingSet3.jnlp. By the way, I'm sort of skipping ahead here.
This demo application requires that you have at least the Java Runtime Environment installed on your system
or it won't run. If you don't have it installed, you can first search Google for just java download and then
Download Free Java Software and install it. Now I'm assuming that you already have Java installed.
We're interested in SwingSet3.jnlp, so click the link, and the application will download to your computer.
We'll quit the browser, we'll go over here and double-click on SwingSet3.jnlp, and the application will run.
Please take some time to explore this application for a few minutes on your own.
You can have a look at various types of containers and components Swing offers.
You can even view the source code down here if you wish.
Let's talk briefly about a history of Swing. Swing is one of five libraries included in the Java Foundation
Classes or JFC, along with the Abstract Windows Toolkit or AWT, the Accessibility API, the 2D API,
and the enhanced support for Drag and Drop functionality. The AWT was Java's first solution for functionality
necessary to operate a windowed application. AWT still is at the core of Swing, which was built on top of
AWT, enhancing it dramatically. The accessibility API provides an interface of your application's components
to assisted technology, such as audible text readers or brail keyboards.
The 2D API contains classes used for painting shapes, fonts, or colors on a 2D surface.
Drag and drop allows users to transfer elements between Java applications and native applications.
But we're going to focus solely on the Swing elements of the JFC, but you may need to be aware of these
related APIs and how they interface with Swing. Next, we'll take a
look at some of Swing's popular features.