Now let's take a look at Swing's popular features.  One of the most popular features of Swing is a
pluggable look and feel. Programmers can easily set the overall look and feel of an application so that it
matches the environment it will run on. Windows and components can have the look and feel that match
existing Windows, Mac, or Unix platforms. Swing also comes with very nice look and feel called metal,
which has some very nice features. Look and feel can also be switched by the user if you wish to allow that
without even closing the application since look and feels are dictated at runtime.
If it's important to you, the look and feel of each component can be customized to create any look and feel you wish.
Additional features of Swing include the ability to display tooltips and also bind keyboard commands to components.
Let's take a look at the SwingSet demo we downloaded earlier to demonstrate.
Start up the SwingSet application, let's click on the JTable for a typical-looking window, and click on View,
and pull down to Look and Feel. You're currently viewing the Nimbus look and feel.
Let's switch it to the Motif Unix-style look, and then let's have a look at the Windows look.
Now, scroll down here to the bottom, and click on ToolTips, and as you roll over this image here you'll see
the basic tooltip I'm sure you're already familiar with seeing.
But now roll over here, and you can see that Swing allows functionality for HTML-styled tooltips as well.
Play around some more here if you wish, and then let's get back to the course.
Another important feature of Swing is that all of its components are lightweight.
Essentially, this means that components are not dependent on the native OS and instead are created at runtime.
That means that Swing will run on Windows, Mac, Unix, Solaris, or any other machine that runs Java.
Lastly, let's talk just for a few minutes about the architecture that Swing is built on top of, and then we'll
move on to create some applications.