Swing uses a common architecture called MVC or Model-View-Controller architecture.
Exactly what is that? Well, model is a representative of the state of a component such as a scroll bar would
contain information about its current position, its width, its minimum and maximum values.
This information does not change if the way the component is represented on the screen changes.
The view is how the component looks on the screen. A window might appear on a Mac or a Windows machine with
a different look and feel even though it's the same component. The controller tells the component how to
interact with events. Events could be a mouse-click, a keyboard command, or gaining or losing focus.
The controller decides how each component will or won't react to an event.
The model, the view, and the controller all act independently, yet they work together seamlessly.
Using the scroll bar as an example, the model provides the information about the scroll bar's width and the
position of the thumb. The view decides how to draw the scroll bar given that info, also knowing whether
it's horizontal or vertical and how to shade it. The controller knows that dragging the thumb or clicking
the end arrows should trigger events. Separation in the Model-View-Controller design allows you to bind
multiple views to the same components. It allows data to be represented say by a table or a pie chart
without affecting the underlying model.
Now that you have a good understanding of what Swing is, let's move forward to the next module and explore
the GUI builder in NetBeans, and we'll build our first application.